<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A decree of Starre-Chamber, concerning printing made the eleuenth day of Iuly last past. 1637.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Court of Star Chamber.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105578</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841305</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841305</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5880</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21452)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 785:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A decree of Starre-Chamber, concerning printing made the eleuenth day of Iuly last past. 1637.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Court of Star Chamber.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie: and by the assignes of Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in part of a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>This edition has the royal arms on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Press law --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Freedom of the press --  Great Britain --  Law and legislation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECREE OF Starre-Chamber, CONCERNING PRINTING, <hi>Made the eleuenth day of July laſt paſt.</hi> 1637.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>Robert Barker,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie: And by the Aſſignes of <hi>Iohn Bill.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:2"/>
            <head>In Camera Stellata coram Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio ibidem, vndecimo die <hi>Iulij, Anno decimo tertio</hi> CAROLI <hi>Regis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day Sir <hi>IOHN BANKES</hi> Knight, His Maieſties At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourney Generall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in Court a Decree drawn and penned by the aduice of the Right Honourable the <hi>Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of the great Seale of England, the moſt Reuerend Father in God
<pb facs="tcp:5880:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5880:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5880:4"/>the Lord <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury his Grace,</hi> the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and Right Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God the Lord <hi>Biſhop of London Lord high Treaſurer of England,</hi> the <hi>Lord chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,</hi> and the <hi>Lord chiefe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> touching the regulating of Printers and Founders of letters, whereof the Court hauing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the ſaid Decree was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and ordered to be here Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and to the end the ſame may be publique, and that euery one whom it may concerne may take notice thereof, The Court hath row alſo ordered, That the ſaid Decree ſhall ſpeedily be Printed, and that the
<pb facs="tcp:5880:4"/>ſame be ſent to His <hi>Maieſties</hi> Printer for that purpoſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the three and twentieth day of Iune in the eight and twentieth yere of the reigne of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and before, diuers De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Ordinances haue beene made for the better gouernment and regulating of Printers and Printing, which Orders and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees haue beene found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be defectiue in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; And diuers abuſes haue ſithence ariſen, and beene practiſed by the craft and malice of wicked and euill diſpoſed perſons, to the preiudice of the publike; And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers libellous, ſeditious, and muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb facs="tcp:5880:5"/>bookes haue been vnduly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and other bookes and papers without licence, to the diſturbance of the peace of the Church and State: For preuention whereof in time to come, It is now Ordered and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That the ſaid former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Ordinances ſhall ſtand in force with theſe Additions, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planations, and Alterations follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:5"/>
            <head>In Camera Stellata coram Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio ibidem, vndecimo die Iulii, <hi>Anno decimo tertio</hi> CAROLI Regis.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mprimis,</hi> That no perſon or perſons whatſoeuer ſhall preſume to print, or cauſe to bee printed, either in the parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, or in this Realme, or other his Maieſties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, any ſeditious, ſciſmaticall, or offenſive Bookes or Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:6"/>to the ſcandall of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the Church, or the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or Governours of the Church or State, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or of any Corporation, or particular perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, nor ſhall import any ſuch Booke or Bookes, nor ſell or diſpoſe of them, or any of them, nor cauſe any ſuch to be bound, ſtitched, or ſowed, vpon paine that he or they ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhall looſe all ſuch Bookes &amp; Pamphlets, and alſo haue, and ſuffer ſuch correction, and ſevere puniſhment, either by Fine, impriſonment, or other corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhment, or other wiſe, as
<pb facs="tcp:5880:6"/>by this Court, or by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Commiſsioners for cauſes Eccleſiaſticall in the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court, reſpectiuely, as the ſeverall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit to be infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon him, or them, for ſuch their offence and contempt.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Item,</hi> That no perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, ſhall at any time print or cauſe to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, any Booke or Pamphlet whatſoever, vnleſſe the ſame Booke or Pamphlet, and alſo all and euery the Titles, Epiſtles, Prefaces, Proems, Preambles, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troductions, Tables, Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:7"/>and other matters and things whatſoeuer thereunto annexed, or therewith imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhall be firſt lawfully licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and authorized onely by ſuch perſon and perſons as are hereafter expreſſed, and by no other, and ſhall be alſo firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Regiſters Booke of the Company of Stationers; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine that euery Printer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending therein, ſhall be for euer hereafter diſabled to uſe or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the Art or Myſterie of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and receiue ſuch further puniſhment, as by this Court or the high Commiſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeverall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:5880:7"/>ſhall require, ſhall be thought fitting.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Item,</hi> That all Bookes concerning the common Lawes of this Realme ſhall be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the eſpeciall allowance of the Lords chiefe Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Lord chiefe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron for the time being, or one or more of them, or by their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; And that all Books of Hiſtory, belonging to this State, and preſent times, or any other Booke of State affaires, ſhall be licenced by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Secretaries of State, or one of them, or by their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb facs="tcp:5880:8"/>And that all Bookes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Heraldry, Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Armes, or otherwiſe concerning the Office of Earle Marſhall, ſhall be licenced by the Earle Marſhall, or by his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; And further, that all other Books, whether of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Phiſicke, Philoſophie, Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or whatſoeuer, ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Lord Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, or by their appointment, or the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, or Vice-Chancellors of either of the Vniuerſities of this Realme for the time being.</p>
            <p>Alwayes prouided, that the
<pb facs="tcp:5880:8"/>Chancellour or Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, of either of the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, ſhall Licence onely ſuch Booke or Bookes that are to be Printed within the limits of the Vniuerſities reſpectiuely, but not in <hi>London,</hi> or elſewhere, not medling either with Bookes of the common Law, or matters of State.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Item,</hi> That euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons, which by any Decree of this Court are, or ſhall be appointed or authorized to Licence Bookes, or giue War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for imprinting thereof, as is aforeſaid, ſhall haue two ſeuerall
<pb facs="tcp:5880:9"/>written Copies of the ſame Booke or Bookes with the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, Epiſtles, Prefaces, Proems, Preambles, Introductions, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Dedications, and other things whatſoeuer thereunto annexed One of which ſaid Copies ſhall be kept in the publike Regiſtries of the ſaid Lord Arch-Biſhop, and Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> reſpectiuely, or in the Office of the Chancellour, or Vice-Chancellour of either of the Vniuerſities, or with the Earle Marſhall, or principall Secretaries of State, or with the Lords chiefe Iuſtices, orchiefe Baron, of all ſuch Bookes as
<pb facs="tcp:5880:9"/>ſhall be licenſed by them reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, to the end that he or they may be ſecure, that the Copy ſo licenſed by him or them ſhall not bee altered without his or their priuitie, and the other ſhall remain with him whoſe Copy it is, and vpon both the ſaid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, he or they that ſhall allow the ſaid Booke, ſhall teſtifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his or their hand or hands, that there is nothing in that Booke or Books contained, that is contrary to Chriſtian Faith, and the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor againſt the State or Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor contrary to good life,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:10"/>or good manners, or other wiſe, as the nature and ſubiect of the work ſhall require, which licenſe or approbation ſhall be imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the beginning of the ſame Booke, with the name, or names of him or them that ſhall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize or licenſe the ſame, for a teſtimonie of the allowance thereof.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Item,</hi> That euery Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of bookes, and perſon and perſons whatſoeuer, which doth, or hereaſter ſhall buy, import, or bring any booke or bookes into this Realme, from any parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, ſhall before ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:5880:10"/>time as the ſame book or books, or any of them be deliuered forth, or out of his, or their hand or hands, or expoſed to ſale, giue, and preſent a true Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue in writing of all and euery ſuch booke and bookes vnto the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, vpon paine to haue and ſuffer ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for offending herein, as by this Court, or by the ſaid high Commiſsion Court reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the ſcuerall cauſes ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, ſhall be thought ſitting.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Item,</hi> That no Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:11"/>or other perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, which shall import, or bring any book or books into the kingdome, from any parts beyond the Seas, ſhall preſume to open any Dry-fats, Bales, Packs, Maunds, or other Fardals of books, or wherein books are; nor ſhall any Searcher, Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or other Officer belonging to the Cuſtome-houſe, vpon pain of looſing his or their place or places, ſuffer the ſame to paſſe, or to be deliuered out of their hands or cuſtody, before ſuch time as the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>London,</hi> or one of them
<pb facs="tcp:5880:11"/>for the time being, haue appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one of their Chaplains, or ſome other learned man, with the Maſter and Wardens of the Company of Stationers, or one of them, and ſuch others as they ſhall call to their aſsiſtance, to be preſent at the opening thereof, and to view the ſame: And if there ſhall happen to be found any ſeditious, ſchiſmaticall or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue booke or bookes, they ſhall forthwith be brought vnto the ſaid Lord Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for the time being, or one of them, or to the High Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Office, to the end that as well
<pb facs="tcp:5880:12"/>the offendor or offendors may be puniſhed by the Court of Star Chamber, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, according to his or their deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; as alſo that ſuch further courſe and order may be taken concerning the ſame booke or bookes, as ſhall bee thought fitting.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no perſon or perſons ſhall within this Kingdome, or elſewhere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print, or cauſe to be imprinted, nor ſhall import or bring in, or cauſe to be imported or brought
<pb facs="tcp:5880:12"/>into this Kingdome, from, or out of any other His Maieſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, nor from other or any parts beyond the Seas, any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, book or books, or part of any booke or bookes, printed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas, or elſwhere, which the ſaid Company of Stationers, or any other perſon or perſons haue, or ſhall by any Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Order, or Entrance in their Regiſter book, or otherwiſe, haue the right, priuiledge, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, or allowance ſoly to print, nor ſhall bind ſtitch, or put to ſale, any ſuch booke or bookes, vpon paine of loſſe and forfeiture of all the ſaid bookes,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:13"/>and of ſuch Fine, or other pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, for euery booke or part of a booke ſo imprinted or imported, bound, ſtitched, or put to ſale, to be leuyed of the party ſo offending, as by the power of this Court, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeverall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Item,</hi> Euery perſon and perſons that ſhall hereafter Print, or cauſe to be Printed, any Bookes, Ballads, Charts, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture, or any other thing or things whatſoeuer, ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto or theron Print and ſet his and their owne name or names,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:13"/>as alſo the name or names of the Author or Authors, Maker or Makers of the ſame, and by, or for whom any ſuch booke, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing is, or ſhall be printed, vpon pain of forfiture of all ſuch Books, Ballads, Chartes, Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and other thing or things, printed contrary to this Article; And the preſſes, Letters and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruments for Printing, wherewith ſuch Books, ballads, Chartes, Portraitures, and other thing or things ſhall be printed, to be defaced and made vnſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable, and the party and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo offending, to be fined, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned, and haue ſuch other
<pb facs="tcp:5880:14"/>corporall puniſhment, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as by this Honourable Court, or the ſaid high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion reſpectiuely, as the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Item,</hi> That no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoeuer, ſhall hereafter print, or cauſe to be printed, or ſhall forge, put, or counterfeit, in, or vpon any booke or books, the name, title, marke or vinnet of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany or Society of Stationers, or of any particular perſon or perſons, which hath or ſhall haue lawfull priuiledge, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:14"/>or allowance to print the ſame, without the conſent of the ſaid Company, or party or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are or ſhall be ſo priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, authorized, or allowed to print the ſame booke or books, thing or things, firſt had and obtained, vpon paine that euery perſon or perſons ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, ſhall not onely looſe all ſuch books and other things, but ſhall alſo haue, and ſuffer ſuch puniſhment, by impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his body, fine, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as by this Honourable Court, or high Commiſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes ſhall require, it ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:5880:15"/>be to him or them limited or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adiudged.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Item,</hi> that no Haberdaſher of ſmall wares, Ironmonger, Chandler, Shop-keeper, or any other perſon or perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, not hauing beene ſeuen yeeres apprentice to the trade of a Book-ſeller, Printer, or Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binder, ſhall within the citie or ſuburbs of London, or in any other Corporation, Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towne, or elſwhere, receive, take or buy, to barter, ſell againe, change or do away any Bibles, Teſtaments, Pſalm-books, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Abcees, Almanackes, or
<pb facs="tcp:5880:15"/>other booke or books whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, vpon pain of forfeiture of all ſuch books ſo receiued, bought or taken as aforeſaid, and ſuch other puniſhment of the parties ſo offending, as by this Court, or the ſaid high Commiſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought meet.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. <hi>Item,</hi> for that Printing is, and for many yeers hath been an Art and manufacture of this kingdome, for the better incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of Printers in their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and iuſt endeauours in their profeſsion, and preuention
<pb facs="tcp:5880:16"/>of diuers libels, pamphlets, and ſeditious books printed beyond the ſeas in Engliſh, and thence tranſported hither;</p>
            <p>It is further Ordered and Decreed, that no Merchant, Bookſeller, or other perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print, or cauſe to be imprinted, in the parts beyond the ſeas, or elſwhere, nor ſhall import or bring; nor willingly aſsiſt or conſent to the importation or bringing from beyond the ſeas into this Realme, any Engliſh bookes, or part of bookes, or bookes whatſoeuer, which are
<pb facs="tcp:5880:16"/>or ſhall be, or the greater, or more part whereof is or ſhall be Engliſh, or of the Engliſh tongue, whether the ſame book or bookes haue been here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly printed, or not, vpon pain of the forfeiture of all ſuch Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh bookes ſo imprinted or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and ſuch further cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and puniſhment, as by this Court, or the ſaid high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought meet.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no ſtranger or forreigner whatſoeuer, be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to bring in, or vent here, any booke or bookes printed
<pb facs="tcp:5880:17"/>beyond the ſeas, in any lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage whatſoeuer, either by themſelues, or their ſecret Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, except ſuch onely as bee free Stationers of <hi>London,</hi> and ſuch as haue beene brought vp in that profeſsion, and haue their whole meanes of ſubſiſtance, and liuelihood depending thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vpon paine of confiſcation of all ſuch Books ſo imported, and ſuch further penalties, as by this Court, or the high Commiſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit to be impoſed.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII <hi>Item,</hi> That no perſon
<pb facs="tcp:5880:17"/>or perſons within the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> or the liberties thereof, or elſewhere, ſhall erect or cauſe to be erected any Preſſe or Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſe, nor ſhall demiſe, or let, or ſuffer to be held or vſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny houſe, vault, ſeller, or other roome whatſoeuer, to, or by any perſon or perſons, for a Printing-houſe, or place to print in, vnleſſe he or they which ſhall ſo demiſe or let the ſame, or ſuffer the ſame to be ſo vſed, ſhall firſt giue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the ſaid Maſter and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the Company of Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the time being, of ſuch demiſe, or ſuffering to worke or print there, vpon paine of impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:18"/>and ſuch other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as by this Court, or the ſaid high Commiſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall Cauſes ſhall require, ſhall bee thought fit.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. <hi>Item,</hi> That no Ioyner, or Carpenter, or other perſon, ſhall make any printing-Preſſe, no Smith ſhall forge any Iron-worke for a printing-Preſſe, and no Founder ſhall caſt any Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, neither ſhall any perſon or perſons bring, or cauſe to be brought in from any parts beyond the Seas, any Letters
<pb facs="tcp:5880:18"/>Founded or Caſt, nor buy any ſuch Letters for Printing; Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he or they reſpectiuely ſhall firſt acquaint the ſaid Maſter and VVardens, or ſome of them, for whom the ſame Preſſe, Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, or Letters, are to be made, forged, or caſt, vpon paine of ſuch fine and puniſhment, as this Court, or the high Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Court reſpectiuely, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth declare, that as formerly, ſo now, there ſhall be but Twentie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Printers allowed to haue the
<pb facs="tcp:5880:19"/>vſe of one Preſſe or more, as is after ſpecified, and doth hereby nominate, allow, and admit theſe perſons whoſe names hereafter follow, to the number of Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to haue the vſe of a Preſſe, or Preſſes and Printing-houſe, for the time being, <hi>viz. Felix King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, Adam Iſlip, Thomas Purfoot, Miles Fleſher, Thomas Harper, John Beale, John Legat, Robert Young, John Haviland, George Miller, Richard Badger, Thomas Cotes, Bernard Alſop, Richard Biſhop, Edward Griffin, Thomas Purſlow, Richard Hodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſonne, John Dawſon, John Raworth, Marmaduke Parſons.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5880:19"/>And further, the Court doth order and decree, That it ſhall be lawfull for the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> for the time being, taking to him or them ſix other high Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to ſupply the place or places of thoſe, which are now already Printers by this Court, as they ſhall fall void by death, or Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or otherwiſe: Prouided that they exceed not the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Twentie, beſides His Maieſties Printers, and the Printers allowed for the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:20"/>
            <p n="16">XVI. <hi>Item,</hi> That euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, now allowed or admitted to haue the vſe of a Preſſe, and Printing-houſe, ſhall within Ten dayes after the date hereof, become bound with ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to His Maieſtie in the high Commiſsion Court, in the ſum of three hundred pounds, not to to print, or ſuffer to be printed in his houſe or Preſſe, any booke, or bookes whatſoeuer, but ſuch as ſhall from time to time be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully licenſed, and that the like Bond ſhall be entred into by all, and euery perſon and perſons, that hereafter ſhall be admitted, or allowed to print, before he or
<pb facs="tcp:5880:20"/>they be ſuffered to haue the vſe of a Preſſe.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no allowed Printer ſhall keepe aboue two Preſſes, vnleſſe he hath been Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or vpper VVarden of his Company, who are thereby al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to keep three Preſſes and no more, vnder paine of being diſabled for euer after to keepe or vſe any Preſſe at all, vnleſſe for ſome great and ſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the publique, he or they haue for a time leaue of the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, to haue or vſe one, or
<pb facs="tcp:5880:21"/>more aboue the foreſaid num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as their Lordſhips, or either of them ſhall thinke fit. And whereas there are ſome Maſter Printers that haue at this preſent one, or more Preſſes allowed them by this Decree, the Court doth further order and declare, That the Maſter and VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the Company of Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, doe foorthwith certifie the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> or the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> what number of Preſſes each Maſter Printer hath, that their Lordſhips or either of them, taking vnto them ſix other high Commiſsioners, may take
<pb facs="tcp:5880:21"/>ſuch preſent order for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing of the ſupernumerarie Preſſes, as to their Lordſhips, or to either of them ſhall ſeem beſt.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, do hereafter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print, or cauſe to bee reprinted, any booke or bookes whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (though formerly printed with licence) without being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiewed, and a new Licence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for the reprinting thereof. Alwayes prouided, that the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner or Printer bee put to no other charge hereby, but the bringing and leauing of two printed copies of the book to be
<pb facs="tcp:5880:22"/>printed, as is before expreſſed of written Copies, with all ſuch additions as the Author hath made.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth declare, as formerly, ſo now, That no Apprentices be taken into any printing-houſe, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then according to this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion following, <hi>(viz.)</hi> euery Maſter-Printer that is, or hath beene Maſter or vpper VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of his Company, may haue three Apprentices at one time and no more, and euery Maſter-printer that is of the Liuerie of his Company, may haue two
<pb facs="tcp:5880:22"/>Apprentices at one time and no more, and euery Maſter-prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Yeomanry of the Company may haue one Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice at one time and no more, neither by Copartner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, binding at the Scriueners, nor any other way whatſoeuer; neither ſhall it be lawfull for any Maſter-Printer when any Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice or Apprentices, ſhall run or be put away, to take an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Apprentice, or other Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices in his or their place or places, vnleſſe the name or names of him or them ſo gone away, be raced out of the Hall booke, and never admitted again, vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5880:23"/>paine of being for euer diſabled of the vſe of a Preſſe or printing-houſe, and of ſuch further pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as by this Court, or the high Commiſsion Court re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit to be impoſed.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe declare, that becauſe a great part of the ſecret printing in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hath been cauſed for want of orderly imployment for Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neymen printers, Therefore the Court doth hereby require the Maſter and Wardens of the Company of Stationers, to take eſpeciall care that all Iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-printers,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:23"/>who are free of the Company of Stationers, ſhall be ſet to worke, and imployed within their owne Company of Stationers; for which purpoſe the Court doth alſo order and declare, that if any Iourneyman-Printer, and free of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Stationers, who is of honeſt, and good behauiour, and able in his trade, do want im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, he ſhall repaire to the Maſter and Wardens of the Companie of Stationers, and they or one of them, taking with him or them one or two of the Maſter Printers, ſhall go along with the ſaid Iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Printer,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:24"/>and ſhall offer his ſeruice in the firſt place to the Maſter-Printer vnder whom he ſerued his Apprentiſhip, if he be liuing, and do continue an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Printer, or otherwiſe to any other Maſter Printer, whom the Maſter and VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the ſaid Company ſhall thinke fit. And euery Maſter Printer ſhall bee bound to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy one Iourneyman, being ſo offered to him, and more, if need ſhall ſo require, and it ſhall be ſo adiudged to come to his ſhare, according to the proportion of his Apprentices and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by the Maſter and
<pb facs="tcp:5880:24"/>VVardens of the Company of Stationers, although he the ſaid Maſter Printer with his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice or Apprentices be able without the helpe of the ſaid Iourneyman or Iourneymen to diſcharge his owne worke, vpon paine of ſuch puniſhment, as by this Court, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth declare, That if the Maſter and VVardens of the Companie of Stationers, or any of them, ſhall refuſe or neglect to go along
<pb facs="tcp:5880:25"/>with any honeſt and ſufficient Iourney-man Printer, ſo deſiring their aſsiſtance, to finde him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, vpon complaint and proofe made thereof, he, or they ſo offending, ſhall ſuffer impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and ſuch other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as by this court, or the high Commiſsion Court reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, ſhall bee thought fit to bee impoſed. But in caſe any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Printer hath more imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then he is able to diſcharge with helpe of his Apprentice or Apprentices, it ſhall be lawfull for him to require the helpe of any Iourney-man, or Iourney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-Printers,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:25"/>who are not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, and if the ſaid Iourney-man, or Iourneymen-Printers ſo required, ſhall refuſe imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or neglect it when hee or they haue vndertaken it, he, or they ſhall ſuffer impriſonment, and vndergo ſuch puniſhment, as this Court ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth hereby declare, that it doth not hereby reſtraine the Printers of either of the Vniuerſities from taking what number of Apprentices for their ſeruice in printing there, they themſelues ſhall thinke fit. Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:26"/>that the ſaid Printers in the Vniuerſities ſhall imploy all their owne Iourney-men within themſelues, and not ſuffer any of their ſaid Iourney-men to go abroad for imployment to the Printers of <hi>London</hi> (vnleſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion ſome Printers of <hi>London</hi> deſire to imploy ſome extraordinary VVorkman o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> VVorkmen amongſt them, without preiudice to their owne Iourneymen, who are Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) vpon ſuch penalty as the Chancellor of either of the Vniuerſities for the time being, ſhall thinke fit to inflict vpon the delinquents herein.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:26"/>
            <p n="23">XXIII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-printer ſhall imploy either to worke at the Caſe, or the Preſſe, or otherwiſe about his printing, any other perſon or perſons, then ſuch onely as are Free-men, or Apprentices to the Trade or myſtery of Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, vnder paine of being diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for euer after to keep or vſe any Preſſe or Printing-houſe, and ſuch further puniſhment as by this court, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall bee thought fit to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:27"/>
            <p n="24">XXIV. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth hereby declare their firme reſolution, that if any perſon or perſons, that is not allowed Printer, ſhall hereafter preſume to ſet vp any Preſſe for printing, or ſhall worke at any ſuch Preſſe, or Set, or Compoſe any Letters to bee wrought by any ſuch Preſſe; hee, or they ſo offending, ſhall from time to time, by the Order of this Court, bee ſet in the Pillorie, and VVhipt through the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and ſuffer ſuch other puniſhment, as this Court ſhall Order or thinke fit to inflict
<pb facs="tcp:5880:27"/>vpon them, vpon Complaint or proofe of ſuch offence or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or ſhalbe otherwiſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as the Court of high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion ſhall thinke fit, and is agreeable to their Commiſsion.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. <hi>Item,</hi> That for the better diſcouery of printing in Corners without licence; The Maſter and VVardens of the Company of Stationers for the time being, or any two licenſed Maſter-Printers, which ſhall be appointed by the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or Lord B. of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, ſhall haue power and authority,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:28"/>to take vnto themſelues ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance as they ſhall think need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and to ſearch what houſes and ſhops (and at what time they ſhall think fit) eſpecially Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſes, and to view what is in printing, and to call for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to ſee whether it be licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or no, and if not, to ſeize vpon ſo much as is printed, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſeuerall offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and to bring them before the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for the time being, that they or either of them may take ſuch further order therein as ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to Iuſtice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:28"/>
            <p n="26">XXVI. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth declare, that it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full alſo for the ſaid Searchers, if vpon ſearch they find any book or bookes, or part of booke or books which they ſuſpect to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine matter in it or them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrine and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or againſt the State and Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vpon ſuch ſuſpition to ſeize upon ſuch book or books, or part of booke or books, and to bring it, or them, to the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, who ſhall take
<pb facs="tcp:5880:29"/>ſuch further courſe therein, as to their Lordſhips, or either of them ſhall ſeeme fit.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. <hi>Item,</hi> The Court doth order and declare, that there ſhall be foure Founders of letters for printing allowed, and no more, and doth hereby nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, allow, and admit theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe names hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to the number of foure, to be letter-Founders for the time being <hi>(viz.) Iohn Griſmand, Thomas Wright, Arthur Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chols, Alexander Fifeild.</hi> And further, the Court doth Order and Decree, that it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:5880:29"/>for the Lord Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>London</hi> for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng unto him or them, ſix other high Commiſsioners, to ſupply the place or places of theſe who are now allowed Founders of letters by this Court, as they ſhall fall void by death, cenſure, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Prouided, that they exceede not the number of foure, ſet downe by this Court. And if any perſon or perſons, not being an allowed Founder, ſhall not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding take vpon him, or them, to Found, or caſt letters for printing, vpon complaint and proofe made of ſuch offence,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:30"/>or offences, he, or they ſo offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhal ſuffer ſuch puniſhment, as this Court, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall think fit to inflict vpon them.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Founder whatſoeuer ſhall keepe aboue two Apprentices at one time, neither by Copartner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, binding at the Scriueners, nor any other way whatſoeuer, neither ſhall it be lawfull for any Maſter-Founder, when any Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice, or Appentices ſhall run, or be put away, to take another Apprentice, or other Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in his, or their place or places, vnleſſe the name, or names of
<pb facs="tcp:5880:30"/>him, or them ſo gone away, be raſed out of the Hall-booke of the company, whereof the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Founder is free, and neuer admitted again, vpon pain of ſuch puniſhment, as by this Court, or the high Commiſsion reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the ſeuerall Cauſes ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, ſhall be thought fit to bee impoſed.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. <hi>Item,</hi> That all Iourney-men-Founders be imployed by the Maſter-Founders of the ſaid trade, and that idle Iourney-men be compelled to worke after the ſame manner, and vpon the ſame penalties, as in caſe of the Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neymen-Printers is before ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5880:31"/>
            <p n="30">XXX. <hi>Jtem,</hi> That no Maſter-Founder of letters, ſhall imploy any other perſon or perſons in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worke belonging to the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or founding of letters, then ſuch onely as are freemen or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices to the trade of found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing letters, ſaue onely in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off the knots of mettle hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the ends of the letters when they are firſt caſt, in which work it ſhall be lawfull for euery Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Founder, to imploy one boy only that is not, nor hath beene bound to the trade of Founding letters, but not otherwiſe, upon pain of being for euer diſabled to vſe or exerciſe that art, and ſuch further puniſhment, as by this
<pb facs="tcp:5880:31"/>Court, or the high Commiſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, be thought fit to be impoſed.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. <hi>Item,</hi> That euery perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, which ſhall at any time or times hereafter, by his, or their confeſsion, or otherwiſe by proof be conuicted of any of the offences, by this, or any other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of this Court made, ſhal before ſuch time as he or they ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, and ouer and aboue their fine &amp; puniſhment, as aforeſaid, be bound with good ſureties, neuer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to tranſgreſſe, or offend in that or the like kinde, for which he, or they ſhalbe ſo conuicted and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as aforeſaid; And that all and
<pb facs="tcp:5880:32"/>euery the forfeitures aforeſaid (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting all ſeditious ſchiſmaticall Bookes, or Pamphlets, which this Court doth hereby Order to bee preſently burnt) And except ſuch Bookes, as the forfeitures are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy granted by Letters Patents, ſhall be diuided and diſpoſed of, as the high Commiſsion Court ſhall find fit. Alwaies prouiding that one moitie be to the King.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. <hi>Item,</hi> That no Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, Maſter, or Owner of any Ship or Veſſell, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoeuer ſhall hereafter preſume to land, or put on ſhore any Booke or Bookes, or the part of any Booke or Books, to be imported from beyond the ſeas,
<pb facs="tcp:5880:32"/>in any Port, Hauen, Creek, or other place whatſoeuer within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> but only in the Port of the City of <hi>London,</hi> to the end the ſaid Bookes may there be viewed, as aforeſaid: And the ſeuerall Offices of His Maieſties Ports are hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to take notice thereof.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. <hi>Item,</hi> That whereas there is an agreement betwixt Sir <hi>Thomas Bodley</hi> Knight, Founder of the Vniuerſity Library at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and the Maſter, VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and Aſsiſtants of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Stationers <hi>(viz.)</hi> That one Booke of euery ſort that is new printed, or reprinted with additions, be ſent to the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie
<pb facs="tcp:5880:33"/>of <hi>Oxford</hi> for the vſe of the publique Librarie there; The Court doth hereby Order, and declare, That euery Printer ſhall reſerue one Book new printed, or reprinted by him, with additions, and ſhall before any publique venting of the ſaid book, bring it to the Common Hall of the Companie of Stationers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer it to the Officer thereof to be ſent to the Librarie at <hi>Oxford</hi> accordingly, vpon paine of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and ſuch further Order and Direction therein, as to this Court, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion Court reſpectiuely, as the ſeuerall cauſes ſhall require, ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
